John Dean Caton Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John Dean Caton Papers 1826-1947 (bulk 1826-1895)
MSS15396
Caton, John Dean, 1812-1895
9,500 items
33 containers
13.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Businessman and jurist. Correspondence, speeches, writings, legal records, financial records, a scrapbook, printed matter, and other material documenting mainly Caton's activities as a lawyer and businessman in Chicago and as associate and chief justice of the supreme court of Illinois.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Basnett, Thomas--Correspondence.; Breese, Sidney, 1800-1878--Correspondence.; Catlin, Thomas D.--Correspondence.; Caton, John Dean, 1812-1895.; Caton, Laura A.--Correspondence.; Caton, William P.--Correspondence.; Churchill, Seldon--Correspondence.; Churchill, W. C.--Correspondence.; Cornell, Ezra, 1807-1874--Correspondence.; French, Austin C.--Correspondence.; Fuller, Melville Weston, 1833-1910--Correspondence.; Gatiss, George H.--Correspondence.; Howell, L.--Correspondence.; Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896--Correspondence.; Judd, Norman B. (Norman Buel), 1815-1878--Correspondence.; Matheson, Joel A.--Correspondence.; O'Riley, Henry, 1806-1886--Correspondence.; Sibley, Hiram, 1807-1888--Correspondence.; Smith, Nathan--Correspondence.; Sweet, E. D. L.--Correspondence.; Treat, Samuel Hubbel, 1811-1887--Correspondence.; Trumbull, Lyman, 1813-1896--Correspondence.; Walker, Pinkney Houston, 1815-1885--Correspondence.; White, Horace, 1834-1916--Correspondence.; Williams, Norman--Correspondence.; Wilson, J. J. S.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Illinois and Mississippi Telegraph Company.; Illinois Starch Company.; Illinois. Supreme Court.; Josiah Macy's Sons--Correspondence.; Oneida Solar Salt Company.
Subjects
Courts--Illinois.; Mines and mineral resources--West (U.S.); Nature study.; Practice of law--Illinois--Chicago.; Telegraph.; Voyages and travels.
Places
Illinois--Commerce.
Occupations
Businessmen.; Judges.; Justices, State--Illinois.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of John Dean Caton, businessman and jurist, were deposited in the library of Congress by Catherine Beveridge and Delia Spencer Field between 1932-1952 and converted to a gift in 1952. Additional installments were given by Beveridge and others in 1953, 1968, and 1982.
Additional Guides
The John Dean Caton Papers are described in Annual Report of the Librarian of Congress, 1932-1933 and 1933-1934. An index to the greater part of the correspondence in this collection is in the Manuscript Reading Room.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John Dean Caton are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1812, Mar. 19 Born, Monroe, N.Y.
1833 Moved to Chicago, Ill. Established first law office in Chicago, Ill.
1834 Member and secretary of the first Illinois political convention held in Ottawa, Ill. Elected justice of the peace, Ottawa, Ill.
1835 Married Laura Sherill Admitted to the Illinois bar
1837 Elected as an alderman in Chicago, Ill.
1842 1864 Associate justice of the Illinois Supreme Court and served as chief justice in 1855 and again from 1857 to 1864
1849 1867 President of the Illinois and Mississippi Telegraphic Co.
1875 Published A Summer in Norway; with Notes on the Industries, Habits, Customs and Peculiarities of the People, the History and Institutions of the Country, Its Climate, Topography and Productions. Chicago: Jansen, McClurg and Co.
1877 Published The Antelope and Deer of America. New York: Hurd and Houghton
1895, July 30 Died, Chicago, Ill.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Dean Caton (1812-1875) span the period from 1826 to 1947 with the bulk concentrated in the period 1826-1895. Caton was the first lawyer who settled in Chicago and was an associate justice of the supreme court of Illinois from 1842 to 1864 and served as chief justice of that court in 1855 and from 1857 to 1864. For more than a generation he was in correspondence with lawyers and public men of his state including those prominent in its history.
Caton’s papers consist of family, professional and legal correspondence, speeches, drafts of an unpublished memoir, other writings, and a scrapbook. The bulk covers Caton's activities as a lawyer in Chicago, as an associate and chief justice of the Illinois Supreme Court, 1842-1867, as chief stockholder and director of the Illinois and Mississippi Telegraph Company, 1849-1867, as an investor in western mines, as a stockholder and director of the Oneida Salt Company, the Illinois Starch Company, and other business enterprises, and as a traveler and contributor of articles relating to nature studies and to the bench and bar in Illinois.
Included are Caton's own letters, those of his wife, Laura A. Caton, his brother, William P. Caton, and other members of his family. Other correspondents include Thomas Basnett, Sidney Breese, Thomas D. Catlin, Seldon Churchill, W. C. Churchill, Ezra Cornell, Austin C. French, Melville Weston Fuller, George H. Gatiss, L. Howell, Josiah Macy's Sons, James F. Joy, Norman B. Judd, Joel A. Matheson, Henry O'Riley, Hiram Sibley, Nathan Smith, E. D. L. Sweet, Samuel Hubbel Treat, Lyman Trumbull, Pinkney Houston Walker, Horace White, Norman Williams, and J. J. S. Wilson.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1826-1842 (Box 1)
  - 1843-1848 (Box 2)
  - 1848-1850 (Box 3)
  - 1850-1852 (Box 4)
  - 1853-1854 (Box 5)
  - 1854-1855 (Box 6)
  - 1855-1856 (Box 7)
  - 1856-1857 (Box 8)
  - 1857-1858 (Box 9)
  - 1858-1859 (Box 10)
  - 1860-1861 (Box 11)
  - 1861-1862 (Box 12)
  - 1862-1863 (Box 13)
  - 1864-1865 (Box 14)
  - 1865-1866 (Box 15)
  - 1866-1867 (Box 16)
  - 1868 (Box 17)
  - 1869 (Box 18)
  - 1870-1872 (Box 19)
  - 1873-1875 (Box 20)
  - 1876-1878 (Box 21)
  - 1879-1880 (Box 22)
  - 1880-1895 (Box 23)
- Speeches and writings (Box 24)
- Mining material, 1862-1882 (Box 25)
- Miscellany, mostly undated correspondence (Box 26)
- Printed matter (Box 27)
- Scrapbook (Box 28)
- Financial papers (Box 29)
- Financial papers (Box 30)
- Correspondence (Box 31)
  - 1831-1842, (9 folders) (Box 31)
  - 1843-1879, 1933-1947, undated, (10 folders) (Box 32)
- Financial and business file, 1820s-1830s, undated, (6 folders) (Box 33)
- Miscellany, 1830-1865 (Box 33)
- Biographical sketches, 1947 (Box 33)